nolan@usernolan.net 206.475.6824

github.com/usernolan linkedin.com/in/usernolan

Summary

I'm a practiced software engineer, enthusiastic learner, and intuitive communicator with 12 years of professional programming experience in a broad variety of demanding technical environments.

Skills + Languages Full-Stack Software Engineering, Data Engineering, Cloud Architecture, DevOps, Product Management

Java, C#, Python, Go, Rust, C, Clojure, TypeScript, Lua, Erlang, Haskell, OCaml

Experience

Founding Engineer — NuID, Inc.

2017-2022

- + Designed and implemented an elastic, highly available authentication API and web-based developer portal using Java, TypeScript, AWS, and Terraform.
- + Designed and implemented a cloud-native developer experience within AWS enabling cheap, on-demand development environments, stateful integration testing, live previews, progressive delivery, and structured observability.
- + Led development and maintenance of open-source front-end and back-end libraries in Java, JavaScript, Go, Ruby, and Clojure, helping hundreds of developers integrate our authentication API into their projects.
- + Hired and led small, distributed teams across engineering and product development which were responsible for onboarding thousands of users onto our authentication service and public key infrastructure.
- + Collaborated with professor of cryptography and ACM Fellow Jonathan Katz to develop a zero-knowledge authentication protocol for which we were granted patents US 10880089, 11496310.

Data Scientist — Microsoft

2015-2017

- + Implemented and maintained data pipelines in Apache Spark and Hadoop-like architectures powering insights dashboards and analyses relied upon by our senior leadership and the CTO.
- + Led engineering and deployment of a machine learning model for device age, informing high-level Windows 10 marketing and delivery strategies across the Windows organization.
- + Designed and implemented a compiler and toolchain in C# for describing compute workflows that improved metric accuracy, reliability, and compute efficiency across our team.

Software Engineer — Rustici Software

2013-2015

- + Contributed to open-source eLearning libraries and browser extensions which increased adoption of an emerging eLearning specification and established new revenue streams for our team.
- + Designed and implemented an open-source conformance suite for testing new and existing specification implementations, leading to an ecosystem-wide improvement in compatibility and improving the visibility of our products.

Education

M.S. Computer Science — Vanderbilt University

2013-2015

- + Thesis: Design Patterns in Concurrent and Asynchronous Systems
- + Project: Distributed Online Record Linkage

B.S. Computer Science — Vanderbilt University

2011-2015

- + GPA: Cumulative 3.777/4.0 Major 3.854/4.0 M.S. 4.0/4.0
- + Completed B.S. and M.S. in 4 years
- + Fine art minor focusing in drawing and printmaking

References

J.D. Hollis — jd@theconsultingcto.com

+ Collaborator on infrastructure at NuID

Pallavi Baral — pabaral@microsoft.com

+ Manager and team lead at Microsoft

Interests

Hiking, Printmaking, Programming Languages, Game Design, Mereology, Music